Hi, Hwei. Thank you so much for, for doing
this. I took this chance to, to learn a
bit more about you,
uh, [laughs] because I think that you have
very cool things to, to share.
Let, let's hope so. Thanks for having me,
and I really look forward to our good
-conversation today.
-[laughs] Cool. Amazing. So
let's get started. Uh, you were, you were
sharing the
-most amazing stories-
-[laughs]
-... so I'll [laughs]-
-That's it
...
I'll go from, from there because there is,
uh, some magic there. So-
-Mm-hmm
-... yeah, before that, maybe a brief
introduction on what we might touch on. We
know each other from the program Data
-Freelancer-
-Yeah
... where, where you h- helped people to
get started in the, their data and AI
freelance journey. And I was curious, um,
preparing for, for this interview, uh,
where all this started. I think there's
always interesting stories there.
Well, your question make me, like, um,
kind of like rewind to many, many years
-ago.
-Yeah [laughs].
Uh, I just, like, graduated from high
school, and, uh, to be honest, I'm, I'm,
-like, not very tech-savvy at that time.
-Mm-hmm.
Like, I just, [laughs] I just learned how
to use the internet for, like, the second
or the third year. Um, [laughs] uh, and
then, um, I came across this thing called
YouTube, and then, uh, for some divine
intervention, I just watched a
Microsoft
Vision 2020 video. So that was like, you
can imagine, like, I mean, we are now in
2025-
-[laughs]
-... but I was watching, like, a, a video
of what Microsoft envisioned Vision
2020 to be
-in twen- in, in 2008.
-Mm-hmm.
So [laughs] and my 2008 high school self
just got, like, blown
away, uh, with that video because it is,
you know, it starts with like, "You can
communicate with, uh, people in another
country." It's auto-translated [laughs].
And then, uh, there's this like, you know,
like, uh, transparent glass panel with
text popping up like, "Oh, your, your
thing is done. Oh, this person has this
update." You'd see dashboard and
everything. At that time, it was just,
like, unfathomable. And so
out of curiosity, because I was, like,
like, too... Was still amazed, uh, with
that thing, I commented under the video,
[laughs] uh, and says like, uh, "Wow,
this is such a great video. I am a high
school graduate, uh,
trying to figure out what should I study
for university. Can anybody [laughs] tell
me what should I study in the university
just to be a part of this magic?" And
then, [laughs] a stranger of, a, a
stranger in the internet, whoever sees
this comment, um,
that person replied that says, "You should
just go for computer science."
-[laughs]
-And I'm like, "Whoever that is, thank you
so much. You're one of the reason [laughs]
why I'm here today, uh, as a data
scientist and AI engineer in 2025."
[laughs]
We need... We all need to thank that, that
YouTube commenter. [laughs]
-[laughs]
-The magic of YouTube.
-Yeah.
-Amazing.
-A gesture of kindness. Yeah.
-Yes.
-So it's sparked by inspiration really-
-Mm-hmm
-... of magic-making.
-Okay, so from, from there, you, you
started the traditional path of computer
science.
Actually, software engineering. So, um-
-Okay.
-So at that time,
-I was living in, uh, a small town-
-Okay
... that is like four hours away from the
capital city, um, of Malaysia, Kuala
-Lumpur.
-Mm-hmm.
And so I pick one university to go and
study. Um, but, uh,
so, you know, like, at that time, you do
foundation in IT, and after one year, um,
I, I was going to, like, computer science.
But then, uh, the, the school admission
says, "Hey, you are the only one who
registered for computer science. Do you
-mind, like, changing a course?" [laughs]
-Really? Okay.
And so I changed, yeah. And so I changed
to software engineering, um, actually
software engineering with mult- with
multimedia.
-Mm-hmm.
-And so in that four years,
um, a fascinating tech came out, which is
called, uh, AR and VR, so augmented
-reality and virtual reality.
-Mm-hmm.
And so me and my friends, we were just,
uh, involved in, um, like,
just projects using augmented reality, and
then we participated in, you know, like,
Microsoft Imagine Cup and things like
this. Yeah, so that was bachelor's time.
-Good time. [laughs] It's been some time.
-Cool, and, and then how... Because now
you're, you're not in Malaysia anymore,
right?
[laughs] Yes. 10 years. 10 years in
Germany now.
-Okay.
-Yeah.
-And how, how do you like Germany?
-It's great.
-Mm-hmm.
-I just saw one of the first Christmas,
Christmas market booths [laughs] today
that's getting set up.
-Mm-hmm. Okay.
-So yeah, Christmas market is one of the
things that I look forward each year in
Germany. But yeah, Germany is
for this 10 years, I think, uh, I really
have to thank this country for it because-
Mm-hmm
... it really, um, grows me as a person. I
feel like, I, I feel like I've, I've
-grown a lot in this last 10 years.
-Really? Okay. And you, you think-
-Yeah
-... uh, that Germany help you to, to,
-to grow personally? In, in which way?
-Hmm. Yeah, I would say fundamentally, uh-
-Okay
-... because, you know, like, I, I've
basically uprooted myself in one culture,
one country, one environment, and then
being put into, like, such a different
environment....
-Mm-hmm.
-And so, I think the greatest things that
Germany has made space for me
is to... is to know who I am as a person,
what I prefer, what my
thoughts and preferences are,
and what do I want. And then I can go
towards that. And so, I would say in
general, like this, um, individual-
individuation, uh-
-Mm-hmm
-... this is what, uh, Germany has given me
-space to grow into.
-Cool. Yeah, I, I've lived in Germany as
well, and I, I think there are some, some
very traditional aspects of, of German
-culture.
-Mm-hmm.
But also there is, um, a big part of
letting everyone be who they want to be-
That's right
-... in all weird ways. They-
-[laughs]
-... they accept and are very- [laughs]
-Yeah
... very
particular, you know. And there is n- not
n- not that much judgment around that
-compared to-
-Yeah
... to other countries or other cultures.
Yeah.
-Yeah. That's right. And so-
-Mm-hmm
... like,
I, I think this is the, the right place,
um, that I'm being put in-
-Mm-hmm
-... to actually grow as a person. Like, I
know I am not anybody's shadow this way.
I'm just me.
Okay, cool. I, I, I remember that, uh, y-
you shared with me some, some time ago
that, that maybe you realized a few, a few
changes when, when you went back to, to
-Malaysia after, after some time, right?
-Mm-hmm.
I, I mean, this happen to me as well. When
I go back to my hometown, home place,
after some times, I realize
I've, I've, I'm not anymore the person
was, that was living there, and, uh, I
cannot fit anymore in that place because
I've grown in different ways, right?
-Yeah, I think no matter where you go-
-Mm-hmm
... if you are an expat, um, you feel like
the version of home that you... that,
that you were familiar with but you
leave, um, will just be a snapshot in the
past because, I mean, Malaysia has grown
so much in these recent years.
-Mm-hmm.
-And so, I think as
an expat, no matter where you go, um,
you feel like
you never belong in the place that, um,
you grow into-
-Mm-hmm
-... but you're also never home anymore,
because home as... has also evolved. But I
don't think that is... I don't
think there's any issue with that because-
-Mm-hmm
-... this is the path that
all of us expats have chosen
and what's most important is to... as long
as you are feeling you, uh,
and as long as you're living
authentically, home is where you are. Home
is not the snapshot that you're left
alone with. Home is also not
like... y- you don't necessarily feel like
100% fitting in, uh, into anything, but I
am pretty sure, like a lot of locals
will also share that, uh, maybe they also
don't feel like they fit into the place
-that they have been like growing up in.
-Mm-hmm.
So I think essentially,
having this... having this experience just
teach us
to realize that... m- to realize that home
is really where you are.
Yeah. That's, [laughs] that's, that's the
goal, right? And to, to
build your home where, where you are, um,
be, be good with, with you, which is a
-journey in, in itself, I, I guess.
-Mm.
-Yeah.
-Interesting. [laughs]
-[laughs]
And where, where in all this, um, AI fits?
[laughs]
Oh, okay. Where, where do we... where
we... what, what did we, uh, have the
story last time? Yeah, software
engineering.
-Mm-hmm.
-And I came to Germany to study, um,
intelligent adaptive systems, so I started
my master's in the University of Hamburg
in 2015, so [laughs] 10 years ago. Um,
yeah. So, uh, that
is, um... that three years, uh, is such a
eye-opener
-because-
-Mm-hmm
... that's when I really learned the ins
and outs, like,
hardcore research
and application of machine learning, deep
learning. I was working on this, uh,
humanoid robotics projects and some
sensors, you know, pairing that with
machine learning and training humanoid
robotics and doing computer vision and all
that.
What, what do you think of, uh, the last,
um, humanoid robot thing that, um, came
-out last week, I think?
-Mm-hmm.
-This, to me, weird-
-[laughs]
... robot with the, with the sweater that
[laughs]... you know, the Neo, Neo I think
-it's called, uh, Neo-
-Yeah
-... something.
-Yeah.
-I think-
-I wouldn't give up things, but the, the,
the humanoid robot, uh, the humanoid robot
that I was working on-
-Mm-hmm
-... uh, also starts with N. [laughs]
-Okay.
-Um [laughs]-
-Interesting.
-Um, yeah. Um-
-Mm-hmm
-... you, you guys sort of share very
similar names. Um, but then
when I think about that version of the
robot with-
-Mm-hmm
-... this version, I think-
-Yeah
-...
it, it, it, it needs some...
-maybe give it five more years-
-Mm-hmm
... uh, for another breakthrough. Um, I
think it's more like
maybe humanoid robotic is developing a
little bit, you know, needing... it, it's
needing more time for all the
non-deterministic situations,
non-deterministic scenarios in real life,
um-
-Gosh.
-So, I feel that... Yeah. [laughs] Uh-
-It takes-
-... if-
... much more time than, than people
expect, right?
Yeah, but I think it's also the, the,
the perception. The audience perception of
it.
-Mm-hmm.
-Because humanoid robotics, this can... It
-can be borderline like uncanny, you know?
-Yeah.
And so, [laughs] and so, mm, the, the mode
of presentation has to be a little bit
-careful because-
-Mm-hmm
... if you, if you present things like,
hey, you have a person that is maneuvering
the robot, which means, like,
-what about the privacy inside? I, I'd-
-Yeah
-... um ... [laughs]
-That, that's definitely-
-Mm-hmm
-... unexpected.
-[laughs] Yeah.
-Yeah. But I think that is the safest way
-for the team-
-Uh-huh
... to actually
s- um,
in a, in a more controllable way
-ensuring the accuracy-
-Yeah
... of the humanoid robot. And so I would
give it some grace, but I also totally
understand
how uncanny it can feel when,
when us just put ourself in the shoes of
the consumer, of the user, and then
extrapolate this presentation
-into what might be in the future.
-Mm-hmm.
Um, so
yeah. If you, if anybody's thinking about,
you know, "Shit, the future is doom,"
[laughs] I can totally understand. Like,
this is just a, I think, the handling of
the presentation into what
the audience might feel. Like, that, that,
that, that can be more considerate.
Yeah. Right, because they, the, the end
goal, I mean, not, not everyone will, will
see it the same way, but
most people would love to have
someone, if it is a robot, it's fine to
then do all the household stuff for you,
right? That, that, that is great. But
it... I feel the technology will
need more time than, than expected, even
if Elon Musk, I think, will, is saying
that
in the next few years will be
there in every home, something like that.
But you have been working, for example,
-um, on this from 2015, right?
-Hmm.
And
you, you think, uh, uh, it has advance a
lot in these 10 years or it's a long
-incremental journey?
-I don't think it's going to be
incremental. I think it's going to be
exponential, uh, from the rate of
development. Um,
I think it still depends on how the world
is moving
and
being somebody who have worked briefly,
um,
in humanoid robotics afterwards, I mean, I
have some years in research, um, also in
synthetic patient data generation feel,
what I think is
I can almost hear two sides of things. Um,
one is the voice of the rest of the world
who are not
in the research and who are not in the
work,
uh, having to apply it. Their, their
concern is real.
-Mm-hmm.
-And so that should not be ignored. That
should be leaned in and listened to. It
has to be a dialogue, um,
for how this, um,
for how this can be done in a way that
essentially is affecting everybody, to be
honest. Um, and people, like, voices from
all sides has to be
-considered.
-Yeah. Yeah.
Um, but then on the other hand, um, for us
who are the practitioners of the field,
of the tech, I see a lot of possibilities.
I see a lot of values to be done,
-um-
-Mm-hmm
... especially in the work that I do for
clients right now. Um,
what I see is
intention really matters and
what
problems are you solving and for who. Um,
humans have to come up with this
first and foremost, and then the tech
comes in too. You know, make it, make it
happen in reality. And so
I think what we can control right now is
whoever is needing the solution and
whoever, like us, is executing or
implementing these solutions, figuring out
for what
and for who. It's kind of
our due diligence.
Um, and when it's done right, I do see a
lot of possibilities, uh, with the current
LM advancements. Uh, and it's just like
the, the, the, the
-general, um, you know, gen AI feel-
-Mm-hmm
... how it's evolving. Uh, it, it is
really fascinating.
Yeah. I mean, we, we of course sh- share
this fascination, right?
-Yeah.
-Because we see all the possibilities. Um,
but in the, in the last years as this has
become a
universal phenomenon and everybody is, is
talking about generative AI and all this
stuff, there are all sorts of, of voices
and things going on. Uh, people are
scared or are,
um, thoughts around, you know, all these
things. AGI will, will take, um, many
jobs and
political things going on. So it's, it's a
mess, right? [laughs] We, we enjoy it
because we, we like to build things. I
think that's, that's the spirit, and we
see it's just, uh, as a technology, right?
Um,
but most people which are not into this
will hear the news, hear whatever, and-...
understand what they, what they can with,
-with the information that they have.
-Hmm.
So there is definitely a bridge there, uh,
to, to... There is a gap to, to,
to fill between these two, uh, worlds.
Right?
-Yeah.
-And, um, yeah. I guess, as you were
saying, it's, it's important to, to pick
the, the right things, uh, in a way and
do it well, but also communicate it in,
in, in the right way, uh, so that people
understand and don't have a weird
expectation or, or fears, you know. Is
that something that, that, that you feel,
that, uh, that you feel, uh, when, when
you work with, with clients or, uh,
interact with, uh, less technical people?
You mean, uh, when deal... When
communicating with less technical clients?
Mm-hmm.
Um, am I understanding correctly that...
Do you think I feel that they care about
the for what and for who, or how should
I... How should I understand your
-question?
-Yeah. Eh, if, if you, you feel that there
is, um, a disconnection between, um, how
you see this technology and
what, uh, less technical people expect
from the technology or what they-
-Mm-hmm
-... um, uh, think about it. If they have
fears or, um,
-how do you say this? Yeah.
-For the clients that c- I come across-
-Mm-hmm
-... usually, um,
usually, it is not like I go and pitch
that they need a solution.
-Mm-hmm.
-It's more like they come to me that says
they need a solution. And so I would say
in my biased
small sample size experience, um,
there's less fear
when a client comes to me and said they
need a certain solution to be made. Um,
there can be, you know, the application of
machine learning or even, like,
statistics, um, like traditional, uh, data
insights-
-Mm-hmm
-... predictive modeling, or the bridge of,
like, taking predictive modeling insights
and then pair that with, um, LM
generation based on these insights. Um,
but usually
when they come to me, they already know
what they want. But then it's up to us to
say, "Okay, what is the best way to go
about it?
Do we care enough for the project to carry
on a good work for the client? Is the for
what and for who aligned with the
implementer as well?" It's like, do I feel
proud to put this piece of project in my
portfolio?
-Mm-hmm.
-Uh, I think this is then regarding the
fit. And if it doesn't fit, just feel free
to, you know, uh, politely excuse
-yourself of this opportunity.
-Mm-hmm.
Uh, but then, uh, what I am striving for
is
try to do things that,
that are for good, because this is part of
my values.
But for good is also kind of like, hey,
it's... it can be anything. Um-
Yeah
[laughs] But for me, it's kind of like
something that I told, told a lot of our
members, our community members, is
when you look back at the things that you
do, even as a freelancer, content creator
or whatnot, um, it's okay to feel cringe,
but you don't really want to feel shame.
-Hmm. Hmm. I see.
-And so it's kind of like intention
-matters.
-Okay. So what's, what's an example of
something that you have been... you have
worked on that you're proud of it?
-Quite many.
-Mm-hmm.
So right now, I am developing
a, an automated tool for a consumer goods
company to
help the data scientists come up with
stability tests. So basically, stability
test is like, um, you know, when consumer
goods have a expiry date, they have r- to
really, like, test their products over
some time and then use some algorithm to
-come up with, um, expiry date.
-Okay.
So to me, I feel like this is a meaningful
project because I get to save the data
scientist's time
who come up with expiry date for consumer
goods, which this consumer goods will be
used by many, many people. And then
another project that I help, uh, to do
is, um, the, the pollutants monitoring of
the Rhine water, uh,
-system.
-Mm-hmm. Okay.
So basically, like, um, basically, like,
part of Germany and the Netherlands share
the same water system. And then, um,
I help build
sort of like a predictive modeling
tool
to kind of like say, "Hey, can we..." You
know, it's all sparse data, so and then
data is kind of like inconsistent and
everything, so a lot of processing is
involved. But that tool now manage to,
uh, kind of like predict
pollutants in time. To say like, "Hey,
when a pollutant is being detected
abnormally
at upstream rivers,
then by this and this time, it, it's going
to flow to the border to the
-Netherlands," and things like this.
-Mm-hmm.
And so this is something that
when being used correctly can really
benefit maybe
the lives of a region of people. Like, I
don't know... I don't know the future
usage of this tool, but the implementation
of it,
the intention behind developing these kind
of tools,
-uh-... to, to me-
-So, in this project... Oh, sorry to
-interrupt.
-No. All good, all good. So this is one of
the, one of the examples of saying
some of the projects that I feel proud of.
Yeah, yeah, that, that, that makes sense.
Just, um, explain a bit, uh, the, the
difference between because that's where I
think it gets confusing for, for people.
For example, for this last project, is it,
um, generative AI? Is it deep learning?
-It is traditional machine learning? Um-
-Yeah, statistical machine learning.
-Okay. What does it mean?
-It is not even
the classical machine learning. Like we
just use statistics as the background
algorithm of it.
-Okay. So-
-No gen AI.
-Mm-hmm.
-No deep learning,
no
neural networks, [laughs] not even random
forests.
-Mm-hmm.
-It's just pure statistics.
-Yeah. [laughs]
-Oftentimes, this is just enough to solve
-the problem reliably.
-Mm-hmm. Mm-hmm. Because, uh, there is
maybe a tendency now to use
generative AI with these large language
models-
-Mm-hmm
-... for, um, to solve any kind of problems
or I... There is this, um, possibility at
least, right?
-Mm-hmm.
-And, um, from
simple things like using ChatGPT as a, as
a consumer, as a user, and you are asking
-it to, to translate apple to Italian-
-Yeah
... and, and it's like using, um,
I don't know, a
-atomic bomb to, to kill-
-[laughs]
-... a mosquito, right? I, I've heard-
-Yeah
-... someone saying that.
-[laughs]
[laughs] Because we, we d- I mean, we
can think about it but, um, the normal
people using ChatGPT doesn't realize that
it's, it's a huge technology, right? And
there are data centers and, uh,
transformers and all i- incredible
technology behind it that transfer for
every simple, uh, conversation that you
have-
-Mm-hmm
-... with ChatGPT, right?
-Mm-hmm.
-While for
many, many things, it's, it's not needed
that, that so intelligent
technology. You know what I mean?
Yeah, but I would say that's a big
distinction-
-Mm-hmm
-... between, um, between the predictive
modeling
models
with, uh, gen AI or LM models because
predictive modeling is largely
discriminative models. And then the LM,
like the things that, you know, ChatGPT or
whoever's coined the term, like AI-
-Mm-hmm
-... the big umbrella term, they are
-largely generative.
-Yeah.
And so they have different usage. So in,
in, in terms of, like, what you said,
you know, I, I want to do translation,
then a generative model can do that very
well because, um, you know, you can, you
can put, like, a, like a, you know, good
prom and then it's going to come up with
an equivalent version of, like, the
translation. But then in predictive
modeling projects, what it needs is
-not creativity.
-Mm-hmm.
What it needs is not generating new stuff
but to reliably, based on past data
points, to accurately predict things. So
if you take time series forecasting as an
example, um, maybe they have very sparse
data, they don't need a model,
like an LM, to tell, "Hey, can you help me
detect anomalies at which point
in time when this happens?" Because a
generative model is most likely to make
-things up.
-Mm-hmm.
But a predictive model, a discriminative
model, is going to train a model based on
the past data
and then if the quality's good and if the
model is... ha- has been trained
successfully, it can then
accurately predict, in time, uh, what
would be the... what would the anoli- amo-
-no- [laughs] anomaly be.
-Anomaly. Mm-hmm.
-Yeah.
-Okay.
So they are for kinda, like, different
usage and that is why
I think
there are certain use cases for, um,
LMs. There are certain use cases that, um,
the discriminative machine learning
models or statistical models will still be
in, in demand because they are inherently
-for different, different things.
-Mm-hmm.
What's the n- the current or, or next
thing that you would like to, to work on?
What's, what that excites you right now?
What are you, um, I don't know,
experimenting with for
-a future client project or...
-Um, I think right now I was too focused on
becoming a s- problem solver for worthy
problems. So-
-Okay
-... for every project that comes, um, it's
important for me to, to satisfy, like, to
be convinced of the for what and for
who. So, if you, if you come with me that
says, "Hey, we, we, we want
-a water pollutant monitoring system-"
-Mm-hmm.
"... to do this and it's going to be used
by, uh, used by this and this person,"
if
I feel convinced of this, like, okay, like
goes, aligns with my values, I'm going to
say yes. Because
to me, based on my previous experience in
academia, in industry, I know where to
look for solutions. And so it's like right
now, the tools that I have a-...
in my toolbox
is machine learning,
deep learning, statistics,
LMs, AI engineering. And so for all of
those things paired with software
engineering, you can basically look for
any solution. You can, you can come up
with any solutions. But what I think is,
um,
it, as long as there's a worthy problem to
solve,
then it doesn't matter what does it take,
because every
freelance project that I'm taking on, it's
just so different. And so-
-Mm-hmm
-... back to your question is kind of like,
it doesn't matter what problem for me to
solve, I know I have the toolbox. I, I
-have enough cards to pull out and-
-Mm-hmm
... fundamentally, I know where to look
for solutions. Um, and so for me right
now-
-Yeah, I love it
-... I, ri- right now, it's kind of like,
yeah, if a data science problem comes to
me, then great. If a
predictive modeling plus LM, um, project
comes to me, then great. Um, I'm just
-looking for worthy problems to solve.
-So
back to, to your beginning, now you know
how to make the magic happen.
-[laughs]
-So you're more focused on
make sure that it aligns with you, right?
Uh, you keep repeating this-
Hm
-... for, for what and for, for who.
-Yeah.
Uh, and so you, you, you
just search for alignment there. That's
the important part for you. And then you
know that you, you, you have so many tools
now, uh, that you can find af-
-solution, right?
-Yeah, that's a very good-
-Mm-hmm
-... uh, depiction of where I'm going. Uh,
-I'm also-
-[clears throat]
I'm also interested to, you know, like go
back to
my main expertise, which is computer
vision. I feel like that is getting-
-Yeah
-... so much less practice since I left,
-uh, my master's degree.
-Okay.
-Yeah.
-So you would like to work on that again?
-Mm-hmm.
-Yeah. It would be great. It's so fun.
-Yeah.
-Yeah, search for it, right? There are-
-Yeah. [laughs]
-[laughs]
-Just need some good portfolio items and
-then I will start applying. [laughs]
-Cool. And, um, the, I guess the, the
other, correct me if I'm wrong, the other
big part for, for you, uh, I don't know if
it is half-half or, or different, is
helping other people
in their
-freelancing or-
-Mm-hmm
... business, uh, journey, right? How,
how-
-Yeah, that's how we met. [laughs]
-Yeah, that's how we met. Yeah.
-[laughs]
-And, and yeah, you shared with me
many things with, about
personal growth and
everything related to this kind of
journey, but how, how it started for you.
Uh,
-when, when you-
-For the coaching?
... decided to... I guess before then
that, uh, from what, what I know about
your journey, when did you
started to have the desire, um, or
conviction to,
uh, be a freelancer, be independent, uh,
something happened there?
Hm. So the first time that I, I
dabble into freelancing was 2020. And at
that time,
so I... [laughs] Continue on the story,
uh-
-Yeah
-... that we left off just now.
-Uh-huh.
-I, I started three years, uh, for my
-master's-
-Mm-hmm
... uh, in intelligent adaptive systems.
And afterwards I took on a full-time job
as a data science consultant, which means
my company sent me to different
organizations and enterprises
across Germany to work on data science
projects, um, for those
companies. And afterwards, um, in 2020,
shortly before that, I feel
like this doesn't align with me so much.
And so I quit. Um, and then I said, like,
I, I really want to, you know, like try to
be, you know, establishing myself and
see, um,
how is it being self-employed. Um, and I
tried that. Um, but at that time
I feel like
it's also like,
how do you say? It's also like an
opportunity come by,
where
back in my master's time I was already
interested in
things to do with medical healthcare, with
machine learning.
-Mm-hmm.
-And in the middle of doing freelancing,
this PhD opportunity came to me. And so I
took on this PhD opportunity and working
that many hours, which means I have to, t-
uh, you know, like give up on
freelancing. Uh, but then
I only took on this, uh, research position
for two years, and then I decided to quit
again. So first freelancing experience is
in 2020. Like, it doesn't last very long.
I think at most, like half a year, one
year. And then I started properly, um,
after I end the contract on this research
position. Um,
and that was
maybe 2024. Uh,
wait.
-2023? 2024. '03 or '04.
-Okay.
So
I was being given a golden opportunity
again, because that time Dave just happens
to open up this data freelancer program,
and then I had the privilege
to join the program, uh, in the first
year. And I could still remember how
much Dave and the community has helped me.
You know, in the first year it's a
smaller group and everybody is kind of
like very close together. Um...... and
Dave is, like, hosting these Q&A calls
like he still does, um, today. And then I,
I started freelancing properly using what
was being taught in the program. Like, I
essentially
apply, tried to apply everything. Um, and
a year after that, I- I think
a year
after that, then
Dave just says, "Hey, we need a customer
success manager and coach." [laughs] "Um,
would you be interested to take on this
position?" And then I was, uh, I was just
being humbled by the trust that Dave, uh,
put on me. I feel like Dave, um, customer
success is not written anywhere on my
resume. [laughs] But
thanks for trusting me. It seems like a
very meaningful role to take on. I'm
willing to try. Like, let's, let's give it
a try. And now it's been, like, one and a
-half years.
-Okay. Yeah. Like, there is so much, I
-feel, to unpack there.
-[laughs]
Uh, when, when you started, uh,
freelancing and, and
y- you des- you, you felt that you needed
help,
-uh, so you, you searched for-
-Mm-hmm
... or you, you come across, uh, Dave, uh,
from, from YouTube, I guess.
-Yeah.
-And, and, and joined the program. What,
what was that, uh, you needed back then?
Hmm. So
when, when Dave's program came out, um...
I actually, before this... So in 2020 I
already joined some, like, freelancing
programs, but that one was more, like,
it's either general freelancing
or, like, a Python base. So, it's not
exactly like machine learning.
-Mm-hmm.
-So when Dave's program is there, I know
that he's a data scientist and he's, um,
doing very successfully in freelancing as
a data scientist. And
his demeanor is just very, you know, down
to earth, as we know, and very smart. And
then I like that he walks the talk. Um,
that is the, the,
the, the decision where I decided to kind
of, like, reach out and express my
interest to join the program. Um, what I
think I needed at that time is
to,
is to essentially
see that I can do it
and I appreciate any kinds of guidance
that if, if anybody who has
w- walked the talk, like, walked this path
before, to see my blind spot, to give me
some advice
that I could apply for myself. Um, this is
why, like, this is mainly why, um, the
rel- the, the, the relevance
of the program itself
paired with
thinking that
I need some... I need somebody experienced
who was on this journey
doing very successfully and I can resonate
with-
-Mm-hmm
-... to help me to go through this process.
Yeah. Makes sense, right? And
wha- what are some, um, I guess, limiting
beliefs or something that you
personally struggled with during, during
that, that first year?
-[laughs] I told-
-There is something that comes to mind or
-no?
-[laughs] Yes. I told Dave, uh, in a later
interview, I said, uh, "Dave, I didn't
have confidence. I outsourced my
confidence to you, and thanks to you, I'm
here."
-Yeah. [laughs]
-"I'm in the game." [laughs]
-I, I-
-And then-
... I think you, you told me that phrase
the first time that we met. I wrote it
-down.
-Oh. [laughs]
And I [laughs], I, I always remembered it.
[laughs]
[laughs] Yeah, and I'm trying to do that
to all the-
-Yeah
-... community members now. Like, I'm like,
"I know what you need, um, based on,
base- based on the fact that I'm also in
the game."
-Mm-hmm.
-Um,
and so
if you, if you can leave the rest to us
and then just say, "I want to go
here," we'll help you get there. And so in
a way-
-Yeah
-... uh, I'm trying to
be outsourced, the confidence, [laughs] as
I, as I unknowingly outsource they've...
-my confidence before. [laughs] Yeah.
-[laughs]
-Yeah.
-You're now passing on, right, to, to them,
to us, to, to the other r- rest of the
people in, in the community?
Yeah, but I also think it's my pleasure.
Like-
-Mm-hmm
-... it, it, it is just such a pleasure to,
-to witness everybody's journey because-
-Mm-hmm
... oh, it's better than movies. It's
better than watching movies. [laughs]
-It's real.
-Like, look at your experience. Like, look
at your journey, like, um, from the first
time that we talk
and until today, you have grown a lot and
you have also achieved some things along
-the way.
-Yeah.
And so this takes, like, you know, you see
a real-life scenario in different people,
-you see the stories in different people.
-Mm-hmm.
Um, I think,
I think my role is just to remind
everybody
what they know already within themself. I
just reinforce that, "Nicola, based on
what we talk, I think you are this and
this person." Um, "If this is your goal,
I help you hold, uh, the... your, your
ideal self in my mind, and in my mind,
every goal that you told me that you're
going to achieve, I consider it, I
consider it done already. And now I'm just
walking this process with you."... e- but
in my mind, it's already done, and I'm
just-
-Mm-hmm
-... waiting for one day in the future
that you'll come back to tell me that yes,
"Hui, I'm already in my ideal self." And,
a- and I'll be just like, "Yeah, I knew
it. I knew it a long time ago." [laughs]
[laughs] Yeah. Yeah, that, that makes
sense. But, um,
what... now that you have seen people
going, going through this, what, what are
the skills to be coachable?
What are the skills to be coachable? Wow,
that's such a great question. Let me
think.
I think it's mostly
-the humility-
-Mm-hmm
...
to see a different
perspective of the story.
-What do you mean?
-A lot of people,
um... so
in my experience, I feel that
I cannot help those people
who cannot believe in another
version of narration. So
what they want is,
"I'm stuck here.
Don't convince me otherwise." And then
they try to... they're not receptive
to the other things. So I would say, first
of all, the humility to accept that
reality has different narration,
and you just have to... other- rather than
seeing it as
good or bad,
see it as pros and cons. And then see
yourself as one avatar in the sandbox,
and says, "I'm here. This is where I want
to go. What is beneficial for me to take?"
And people with narrate, a certain
narration, they are very s- you know, very
-convinced of something-
-Mm-hmm
... when I see that it, this convincing
reality
does not serve them, uh, and if they,
if they are not ready
to accept
other possibilities, other narration that
says, "Hey, maybe you can look into here
and that," um,
I, I think if they are very... if, if they
decide to stay in this narration, there's
-nothing that I can do.
-I see.
-Yeah.
-So, and during-
Also, this is one. Second would be
accountability.
-Okay.
-This is what we do every week, Nicolas.
-[laughs]
-[laughs] I know that part well.
-[laughs] Yeah.
-Okay. But-
-Accountability. Do they follow up?
-Mm-hmm.
Do they follow through, um,
with, with the things that they should be
doing, they said they would do?
-Yeah. So-
-Because action moves the needle, right?
-Mm-hmm.
-Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah, yeah, of course. I, I was
curious to, to
dig a bit deeper on, on the first part
that you... uh, what you said, right?
-Mm-hmm.
-So I'm hearing that if someone
has
-their own narration, es-
-Hmm
... so it, like a story that they tell
themself
and they,
they are not willing to
see another story-
-Hmm
-... but they want to g- to get somewhere,
uh, to their goals. And y- you, you help
them s- realize that, uh,
to get there, they need to, to change, um,
the narration,
right? So if they-
-Mm-hmm
-... are not flexible in that way or they
don't
l- listen that there is another, um, uh,
narration, there is another story that
-serves you better to, to get there-
-Mm-hmm
... um, it's difficult to, to help
someone stuck in that situation. Is that
what, what you mean?
-Yeah. So-
-Mm-hmm
... if they, i- if they feel that it is
more,
it is more valuable to hold onto the
current narration that put them in current
situation
and they are not ready to
see elsewhere. You know, like even to be
open for the possibility, the other
narration of
maybe there's some other things that you
can still try or maybe there is some
interpretation of your assumptions, uh,
that you can maybe tweak a little bit.
Maybe, maybe that, that can be... that can
move you forward a little bit. So, um,
yeah. So if, if they,
if they feel more secure by holding onto
this,
-this narration-
-Mm-hmm
... um, I will honor that. I will make
space. I- I will make space for that as
well to say that, "It's okay. I can see
that you're not ready to, to, to
explore or this narration, um, uh, at this
moment." And so, um,
I, I, I feel that
it is also important to
make them feel okay that this narration
right now that
they, they ho- like, they hug, like
hugging a log just to not drown-
-Mm-hmm
-... um, it's okay to
acknowledge that and give space
for them to
-do this until they are ready again.
-Okay. Yeah. Yeah, I recognize
your... y- you have this, um...... way of
helping
people. Uh, yeah, that is, uh, you know,
everyone has their own, um,
way of going to
coach someone in, in these situations,
right?
-Mm-hmm.
-Uh, there are some more, um, I don't know
how to call it, more strict in a way, uh,
but y- you can
go and, and
take someone from where they are,
uh, as you've said, acknowledge that they,
in this moment, they might need something
else, right, that you cannot force them,
uh,
-right? That is a more gradual journey-
-Hmm
... uh, that comes with, with whatever
time and type of journey-
-[laughs]
-... uh, someone needs, right? [laughs]
Have you heard about the story of the
mushroom man?
-Mushroom... No.
-Okay. So, um-
-Tell me.
-I watched this story from the internet, so
I don't know where to cite this from, but
this story's-
-Yeah
-... stuck with my head. And-
-Hmm
-... I've been sl- I've been secretly
applying to all of you guys [laughs] all
along.
-Oh. Let's see.
-So, [laughs] so the mushroom man is,
hmm, there's a guy who is so convinced
that he is a mushroom, he's not a m-
-human.
-Okay.
-So, [laughs], a guy is so convinced-
-[laughs]
... that he's a mushroom, and so he just
take this umbrella and then just stood on
one side all along. Like, he just wants to
be a mushroom. Like, he's so-
-Okay
-... convinced that he is a mushroom.
-Believe me, this.
-Yeah. [laughs] And then, of course,
other people who care for him will say
like, "You're not a mushroom. You're
human." Like, "Come on." [laughs] It's
like-
-Mm-hmm
-..."Look at yourself. You don't look like
a mushroom," but that guy is just so
convinced to be a mushroom and nobody can
change his mind. Um,
and so one day, a person comes along
and [sighs] he just take another umbrella
and just sit next to him.
-Uh-huh.
-And then that mushroom guy said,
"Hey, what are you doing here?" And then
that guy just says like,
"I'm also a mushroom." [laughs]
And then that guy says, "Huh. Oh, we're
mushroom friends now."
-[laughs]
-And after, you know, sitting, sitting with
that guy for, for some time, that, that
guy just started to stand and
walk. And then the mushroom man just
freaked out. And then [laughs] that
mushroom is like, "Hey, you're a mushroom.
How can you do this?" And then that guy
just said, "You don't know? It's 2025.
Mushrooms can walk."
-[sniffs]
-And then that guy says, "Huh. Interesting.
Are you... Okay? Mushrooms can walk?" And
he's like, "Of course. All mushrooms can
walk this year, starting this year." And
then the mushroom guy just stand up and
walked. And so the moral of the story is,
um,
righteousness is not my goal
-in coaching.
-Hmm.
Um, the intention to making somebody, um,
seeing the potential in somebody, that
this person is not a mushroom, is a human,
and he has the place that he needs to go.
Um, I don't have to be right. I just have
to
try my best
to have the intention to get this person
into where
-they want to go.
-Yeah. Now, it, it makes... Yeah,
definitely, it's how you're helping us. It
makes sense. [laughs]
-[laughs] Now you know my trick. [laughs]
-Yeah. [laughs] No, this is great. Yeah,
and I, I mean, it's... These stories help
you to
fix, uh, fix some, some ideas, but, you
know, I, I, I see, uh, you know, where,
where...
from where you, you come from, and, uh,
different people need different things.
Someone
works better with a
-carrot and stick approach, and, uh-
-[laughs]
... someone who... It's, it's a mush-
someone is a mushroom. [laughs] They need
a different approach to this. Uh, yeah,
that, yeah, I can relate to that. It
-makes, makes sense. And, uh-
-Yeah, it just happen that I don't have to
-be right.
-Yeah.
I don't have to, I don't need to have
another people told me that I'm right
for me to feel good about myself. Like, I
just, like, I care about another person,
and for this care, uh, I would do my best.
I know, I know my goal. That my goal is
-not to be right.
-Hmm. Mm-hmm. Is to, to get someone
where they want to go. Yeah.
-Okay, cool. So that's, that's-
-[clears throat]
... let's say, the first, uh, skill that,
that, that you mentioned. The second
-important one is accountability, right?
-Hmm.
And, and so why
some of us
ask everyone
[laughs] some- sometimes we, we are not
able to
do what we say that, uh, we want to do.
Why we need that
accountability?
Accountability
helps you make progress. And there can be
many reasons why, mm, you cannot do
what you wanted to do. You might be
lacking
skills. You might be lacking some tools.
You might be lacking the permission that
only you can give to yourself. And another
people just have to remind you that, um,
the power is not outside. The power is
inside.
-Hmm.
-And these are the things that
I think in life we just rely on the
kindness of another person
to help you move forward, and that is how
we,
that is how we choose to interact with the
world, to...To be willing to accept the
goodness from other people, and then pass
it forward.
Okay.
[sniffs] Okay.
Yeah, you know, I was, I was expecting a
totally different, uh-
-[laughs]
-... totally different answer, and I'm
realizing, yeah, that
I don't know, in the couple last days,
and now I'm connecting random dots.
-[laughs]
-Uh,
[laughs] excuse me if it doesn't make
sense. But no, I think it makes some sense
because they're... When I think about
accountability or these kind of topics,
uh, coaching and, and people going through
some personal development journey, I feel
the
predominant narrative online, especially
YouTube or
the, the influences that I see, thanks to
the algorithm, algorithm of whatever, are
quite strong, right? You know, more
masculine energy in a way.
-Mm-hmm.
-The Tony Robbins or
this kind of motivational stuff, right?
Makes sense?
-Mm-hmm.
-While in, in your answer, I feel
-definitely a different energy, uh-
-Okay
... that is not the predominant one
because predominant is louder and
definitely
-more masculine. I, I feel there-
-Mm-hmm
... at least, uh, yeah, as I said, what,
what we see online, et cetera, is more
men doing this, at least, uh, what, what I
receive from
the algorithm. And while
the, your angle is, is, is different in
this-
-[laughs]
-Yeah. And it's, it's a, it's good that
-there is another angle, right?
-Yeah.
And that we normally don't, don't see.
What do you think?
Yeah, I'm glad that I contribute a little
bit to that. Uh-
-Yeah
-... but I also see that, um,
-I think you just have to look, um-
-Mm-hmm
... advice like this also exists on the
internet.
-Yeah.
-Um,
I think it's more like,
if, if you don't realize, like, you just
don't know what you don't know. I think,
and this happens with a lot of people, and
especially the, the design of the
-algorithm is more like bubble-like.
-Mm-hmm.
Like, you get more of what you look at and
what you consume. And so you, you know,
from time to time, look, look the other
side. [laughs]
Yeah. [laughs] You have some
recommendation for the other side? What,
what, what are some
resources or some people that influenced
you?
Oh, resources and people. Um,
I don't know, where do I start? [laughs]
It's like in the, in, in which topic?
Yeah, in this kind of, uh, I think now we
are in the
personal development
or, um,
doing something that you have never done
before.
-Mm-hmm.
-In this case, it's, uh, your business,
-your freelance journey.
-Mm-hmm.
And so there is that struggle to do
something that
you have not done before. And so you might
need
what we are talking about, right? Changing
your story, uh, accountability, someone
-that helps you.
-Hmm.
So, in this realm of
personal growth,
what, um, most influenced you or you like
to read,
-look up to-
-[laughs]
... go back to?
I am currently reading... So, go back to,
I have one principle book that help me,
like that is the guiding light, uh, of, of
my life.
-Mm-hmm.
-And then some supplementary books. And,
um, but yeah, I can share them. So,
my guiding principle resource
-is, uh, Diamond Sutra by the Buddha.
-Okay.
And then I am currently reading,
I'm currently reading Tao Te Ching by Lao
Tzu.
-Okay.
-Um, but they are very meta, they're very,
they're very like [laughs] they are for
people like me who always contemplate the
meaning of life. [laughs] And, but the
third one-
-Mm-hmm
-... but the third one that I can recommend
is, uh, The Way of Integrity by Marta
Beck.
Okay.
-What can you tell me-
-Yeah
... about these three books? Or I'm
curious about the first one
since it's your-
-Hmm
-... um, guiding principle. What-
-Yeah
-... what there is in there?
The Diamond Sutra essentially says that,
um,
everything tangible that you can see in
this world,
um, is kind of like
it's ever-changing. So, it's kind of like
a dream. It's kind of like a dew, and like
a morning dew. It's kind of like, um,
illusion. It's kind of like a shadow.
Um, it's kind of like
a
thunder, um, and we should see the world
this way. And so that has given
me,
that has given me a sense of saying that
I should not kind of like try to cling on
something. Um, I should be really fluid,
like if I want to, uh, enjoy the world the
right way. Um,
and so one of the stories in there, it
says,
"If you're drowning and then you happen to
hug a log," like a big piece of wood.
-Mm-hmm.
-"And then that has saved your life. Um,
but then
since you're now safe, you're, you're not
drowning anymore, you have come to the
land.
But maybe out of
security, you feel like this log is so
important for you, it has saved your life,
so you just hug it to walk it."But who
knows your next quest is to climb the
mountain. Like, you cannot... Since the
lock has saved you already, you should let
it go because your next quest is climbing
a mountain. That lock is not going to
-serve you.
-Hmm.
And so, that main guiding principle is
kind of like, say,
everything is as is, as happened. Um, for
example, our podcast now
-is as happened.
-Mm-hmm.
It's going to end in, I don't know, like
20 minutes' time.
And I should not
-cling on it.
-Yeah.
I should not think about, "Oh, damn, I
should change something about it."
-Hmm. I see.
-Like also in freelancing, it's like... Uh,
in freelancing, you have to have a level
of grace, uh, and compassion to yourself
for the courage to come out. If you
always said, "I have to be perfect. I
cannot make any mistakes," sorry, you live
in a classroom. You're not living in the
-real world.
-Hmm.
Um, if you are living in the real world
and you don't want to get to insanity
[laughs], just try to
do a small experiment, see what it comes
back. And if it is not the outcome that
you want, just pivot and do better next
time.
-Yeah.
-So, like don't hug the lock when you have
to climb the mountain. Yes, the lock has
saved you, it has served you in the past,
but time to move on.
-Yeah. That-
-Yeah
... that's a, that's a great metaphor,
yeah.
-Yeah, so it's kind of like-
-Mm-hmm
... I don't see you, Nicola, as Nicola the
coachee, because I know
it just happened in this moment that we
met and I'm being put in a position to
give you some advice, and you're in the
position of needing some advice. But this
is not forever. Like, this is not
permanent. At some point, these
-three that I l- look after will grow.
-Mm-hmm.
Like, you're going to be a different
Nicola, and I don't see you, Nicola, as
the first version anymore. Like, I should
see you as an ever-changing. And, eh, this
is, this is the... This is what I think
the, the way that I prefer to look at
life. Everything.
-Mm-hmm.
-Like people, person, environment,
-everything.
-Hmm. Makes me think of... It ki- I feel
it's kind of a translation of this, um,
that what serves, served you to, to get
here, will serve you to get-
-Yeah
-... somewhere else, right? We have
-different-
-Yeah
... whatever, phases, challenges, uh,
growth path.
-Mm.
-And something, you need something to
get somewhere, eh, but then it won't help
you to get somewhere else because it's-
-Yeah
-... constantly evolving
journey and challenges and, and stuff,
yeah.
Perfect. This is a perfect interpretation.
[laughs] Yeah. And what, what about the...
What was the, the third book that, that
-you mentioned?
-The Way of Integrity by Marta Beck.
Mm-hmm. And what's the, the message from
there, that one?
The message is to really honor your own
truth.
-Mm-hmm.
-And so, uh, it described like this theater
play by... It's called Inferno.
Um, so I think it's like, maybe it's
Italian story, you know? Like,
-maybe let me know. [laughs]
-I'll, I'll look into it. I mean, the-
-[laughs]
-... the Inferno from, from Dante is where
-it all started.
-Yes.
-Yeah.
-It's from Dante, yeah.
-Mm-hmm.
-So, that book is about taking Dante's
-Inferno-
-Oh, I see. I see
-... into examining our life.
-Okay.
And so, it says that it, it goes
through... You have to go through the
-center of the Earth-
-Mm
... and then go to the inferno
and then coming out from the other side.
And so that book is such a-
-Mm-hmm
-... supernova for me. Like- [laughs]
-Okay.
-Because, um,
back then, I just take every advice as is
and thinking that if I apply them, um, I'm
going to get success or get happier. But-
-Mm
-... I forgot to examine myself, like if
that advice is made for me or not. Like,
do I see myself in this or do I have a
level of understanding
-that this thing fits me or not?
-Hmm.
Um,
and the process of doing that is then to,
to
-find-
-[laughs]
... the truth slowly. And that book, The
Way of Integrity, it's basically like
explaining or practicing or making you
realize what are the ways that you can
find your own integrity. And so you have
this inner truth as your anchor. And
everything has to filter through this,
and then you get a sense of clarity, um,
-when dealing with a lot of noise.
-I see. So it's like helping you
to, um,
filter the advice and whatever,
[clears throat]
whatever people tell you
instead of following, uh, everyone in all,
in every
-direction.
-Yeah. Yeah. It's more like
there are two kinds of heart. Um, there
are two kinds of
hardness,
um, that, that we face. Um,
one kind of heart is if you're a fish,
then if you want to swim to the ocean and
then, you know, it's a different
environment, you just have to push on,
right? Like you have a, you know, you'll
be stronger as a different, as a stronger
fish. You'll maybe swim faster or
anything. But another kind of heart is you
don't know who you are, you don't even
know you're a fish-
-Yeah
-... and then you're trying to compete with
monkeys climbing the tree, and then
you'll be stuck thinking, "Why are the
other monkeys just seem so..."So light and
easy and so effortless in climbing the
trees, because you don't even know, like,
and, and you're kind of out of breath.
[laughs] You're not as good as they are.
You're not achieving the height that they
-are, but you're half dying.
-Mm-hmm.
Uh, that's because you don't realize that
you're a fish. Like, this is not your
lane. Like, go back to the water, like,
and, and, you know, swim towards the
-ocean.
-Yeah.
-Did you, did you, um,
experience some- something like that?
There was, there was a time where you felt
-you were trying-
-Yeah
-... to do-
-Three times.
-Yeah? Okay.
-Three times that I have to be almost
bedridden [laughs], I'm in a lot of pain-
-Mm-hmm
-... uh, to realize, uh, I'm not supposed
to do a certain things, and usually that
comes in terms of, um,
the career choice,
-um-
-Mm-hmm
... and, uh, environment
and, uh, my
-attitude trying to climbing the trees-
-Hmm
... uh, while not knowing myself. So yeah,
I have had
three burnouts in the past 10 years, and
the first one was, um, during my software
engineering time, and the second one was
during my PhD time, and no...
During my, uh, data science consultant
time, and then third time was during my
-PhD time.
-Hmm.
And what did you real- realize?
Why you were, um... What
made it clear for you that you were doing
what you were
not supposed to do or was not?
I realized that
I, I never think about checking in with
myself
if,
if being in an environment or doing a
certain thing
will make me respect myself more or less.
So I didn't... So it's more like I
keep looking out
and I, I try doing things and I try to
come up with a good result, good
performance, um,
but then I don't know what I'm made of.
Um-
-Hmm.
-So it's kind of like... Uh, it's kind of
like
I am trying my very best
just trying to survive instead of
thriving, and that comes in many, many
ways. Maybe it is with
the pace of the project. Maybe it's with
the nature of the project. Maybe it's with
the nature of the environment, of what is
demanded of you, um, and, and
this kind of, uh, self-awareness came,
uh,
after taking me through excruciating
physical pain, um, to, to
realize that maybe I should look at what
I'm made of. [laughs]
-Yeah.
-So you, you feel you were ignoring
maybe
earlier signals, right? You, you had to
-get to physical pain.
-I'm ignoring all the subtle and obvious
-signals-
-Mm-hmm
... that until my body literally can't
move anymore,
-for me to say, "Stop."
-Okay.
Otherwise, I would still keep moving. Like
otherwise, I wouldn't have learned this
lesson. So my body was compassionate
enough to take a
breakdown, to remind myself that, hey,
this is not you. Like, this is
... You're not... Uh, you're, you're,
you're a different vehicle being put on
-different purpose.
-Hmm.
-Yeah.
-What, what are those signals
that someone in, in a similar situation
might catch before
getting to
-pain?
-Hmm.
At, at first, I would say
it is, um, little discomfort here and
there, and that might come in terms of
emotions, that might comes in terms of
sensations. Um, and then, uh, the
next thing would be you're trying to
overcome them-
-Mm-hmm
-... but
you feel that you are slowly giving up on
yourself or betraying yourself. Like,
you're, you're so
kind of like betraying your own truth, um,
in order to get better, if that make any
sense. Um,
and then you
keep
giving in. So
-you slowly find yourself-
-Mm-hmm
... grinding
more like,
more like you, more like you feel like you
grind yourself off, that nothing is left.
Like you're, you're le- you're slowly
losing your life force instead of, um,
instead of feeling like,
-"I'm still myself doing this."
-Hmm.
Yeah. It, it's going to feel like, "I keep
running and running and running, but for
what?" And maybe your logical brain is
going to convince you, "Ah, it's for
-this," you know, the-
-Hmm
... this, um,
nice achievement,
and it's for me to prove to myself that I
can do this,
um-But yeah, um,
this is going to... This is kind of like a
slippery slope where you, you betray
-yourself again and again and again. Yeah.
-Yeah. And y-
-Those are the signs.
-Yeah, definitely.
-It happened to me-
-Those are the signs. And then you, you
-wake up and then you think like-
-Mm-hmm
...
"Why am I doing this?" Like, like, "Where
am I?" [laughs]
Yeah, exactly. Wanted to say exactly the
same.
-[laughs]
-But
it happened to me in the, in the past
going
into work in the morning,
you know. You, you get there, you sit at
your desk, you look around and you say,
-"What am I doing here?"
-[laughs] Yeah.
-[laughs]
-Time to look inside.
-Yeah.
-That's a message for you. Read the
-message. [laughs]
-I see. And so you... It's
interesting, you, you, you said that this
happened to you, um, three times. So it
was different things that you discovered,
or you went,
you went back to, uh, something similar
that, I don't know, uh, catch you
in a different way?
Same feeling, different environment,
different faces, different projects. But
the feeling is the same.
-Okay.
-The feeling is that
I didn't stop myself right there
and allow myself to do the things or be
somewhere or... well, generally do
something
that make myself respect me less.
-Hmm.
-That's the, that the... That's the
question that I didn't think of
questioning myself back then, if this
would be my
decision filtering process that will make
a lot of life easier.
I see. And there, there were... There was
a part of you
in the second or third time that says
why you, you felt again into this
-or, or not?
-No, second and third time I managed to
-catch myself easier.
-Okay.
Um, and being different from the first
time. The first time is kind of like I
just graduated university, this is my very
first job. I have to do my very best as a
-A+ student. [laughs]
-Mm-hmm.
You know, like
score perfectly, uh, for everything that I
do.
-Yeah.
-Um, when I had the first burnout, I
actually doubted myself. Like, I actually
asked myself, like, "Why am I so useless?"
-Like, "Why can't I do this?"
-Yes.
Um,
but second and third time, no. Like second
and third time it's like, "Ah, there it
goes again." [laughs] "I thought I have
pivoted, but looks like I have not pivoted
-enough." [laughs]
-[laughs] I see. Okay.
-Yeah.
-That makes sense. There, there was some...
You feel external pressure, and
especially in the first time or something
that you, um,
that it was coming from, from the past or
something that you learned when, when you
were younger, um, that you needed to be
this A+ student, uh, score everything
-at, uh, the best-
-Hmm
... you felt like some external pressure
back then?
I wouldn't think it's an external
pressure. I think it is more like the...
-I misunderstood myself.
-Hmm.
Um, only recently, two to three years ago,
that
I change my perspective
on my existence in the world.
So
only up until two to three years
ago,
I used to think that my existence
is to be of use by others,
is to
lose my
shapes and forms
and then putting myself down to the dust
and to just serve others, and that is
love.
-Hmm. Okay.
-And that is contribution. That was my
thinking-
-Mm-hmm
-... back then. Um,
and yeah,
well since this last two to three years,
I've changed a lot. [laughs] I'm living a
much better life right now, uh, and
continue to do better. But yeah,
um, that, that, that
shift in perspective
that I am my own person, I have my shapes
and forms and boundaries. This is where I
end, this is where other start. [laughs]
Uh, I can have my own preference. Uh,
I
exist in the world, therefore
I have the right to interact with the
world as me.
-Mm-hmm.
-Um, that might sound crazy for a lot of
people hearing this right now, but this is
seriously... If I want to be totally
honest, I only s- started
embodying that two to three years ago.
Yeah. I, I think it... most people are,
are struggling with that. Is, is not, not
strange. Or maybe
it's strange for someone because they have
not thought about it.
-Hmm.
-But, uh,
-many, many people-
-I'm not going back. I'm-
-Yeah.
-It's irreversible anymore. [laughs] I'm
-not going back. Never ever.
-Of course not, yeah.
-[laughs]
-No
-way.
-Yeah. That's, uh, yeah. That's amazing
that, that
you have been able to, to do that, you
know. It takes,
it takes, um... Some people, it takes a
lot of time and-
Mm-hmm
... you don't even realize because when,
when
the past you, uh, were not realizing, was
not realizing
what was happening, right? Uh, or not
fully,
-uh-
-Mm-hmm
... to be able to, to break out of it and,
as you said, understand your boundaries
and that
you exist for yourself with your own
tastes and goals, et cetera, et cetera.
-Yeah.
-You're not living just for the others. And
it's amazing to see you
-shine now.
-[laughs]
I'm, I'm so curious to,
to see where this
-path will, will lead y- lead you.
-Mm-hmm.
-I would want-
-Yeah
... you to share more of this because
-it's-
-[sighs]
It's so important and you, you explain in
such easy and understandable
-terms.
-Sure. We'll be glad to.
-Share.
-We'll be glad to. Let's see how things go,
-but-
-Okay
... I'm feeling hopeful. I'm feeling very
hopeful. [laughs]
[laughs] I know.
That's great. Okay. I think that this is,
um, a nice
-ending.
-That's great.
Thank you so much, Hui, for, for the
conversation.
-Thanks for having me.
-I learned a bit more about you and, uh,
you have shared so many interesting
things. I hope people can,
um, use them
to,
to grow them, themselves as well.
Yeah. Really, Nicola, thank you so much
for inviting me to do this. Uh, I am not
used to talk about myself. I hope this
ends well. But in any case, I've enjoyed
our conversation today and, uh, thank you
for having me.
-Thank you, Hui.
-Thank you.
Bye. See you.