One kind of hard is if you're a fish
then if you want to swim to the ocean
and then you know like it's a different
environment you just have to push on
right like you have a you know you be
stronger as a different as a stronger
fish you maybe swim faster or anything
but another kind of heart is you don't
know who you are you don't even know
you're a fish and then you're trying to
compete with monkeys climbing the tree
and and you're kind of out of breath
you're not as good as they are and my
high school self just got like blown
away. That person replied that says you
should just go for computer science. And
I'm like whoever that is, thank you so
much. You're one of the reason why I'm
here today uh as a data scientist and a
engineer in 2025.
Especially in the work that I do for
clients right now. Intention really
matters and what problems are you
solving and for who humans have to come
up with this first and foremost and then
the tech comes in. There's a guy who is
so convinced that he is a mushroom. He's
not a human. And so he just take this
umbrella and then just stood on one side
all along. And so one day a person comes
along just take another umbrella and
just sit next to him.
And then that mushroom guy said, "Hey,
what are you doing here?" And then that
guy just says like, "I'm also a
mushroom." That guy says, "Huh? Oh,
we're mushroom friends now." And then
after you know sitting sitting with that
guy for for some time that that guy just
started to stand and walk
and then the mushroom man just freaked
out. Hey you're a mushroom. How can you
do this? You don't know it's 2025.
Mushrooms can walk. Huh? Interesting.
Are you okay? Mushroom can walk. And he
said of course all mushrooms can walk
this year. Starting this year. And then
that mushroom guy just stand up. And the
moral of the story is I don't have to be
right. I just have to try my best to
have the intention to get this person
into where they want to go.
[Music]
Hi Way, thank you so much for for doing
this. I took this chance to to learn a
bit more about you.
uh because I think that you have very
cool things to to share.
Let's hope so. Thanks for having me and
I really look forward to our good
conversation today.
Cool. Amazing. So, let's get started. Uh
you were you were sharing the most
amazing stories. So, I
I'll go from from there because there is
uh some magic there. So yeah before that
maybe uh brief introduction of what we
might touch on. We know each other from
the program data freelancer
where where you have helped people to
get started in the their data and AI
freelance journey and I was curious um
preparing for for this interview uh
where all these started. I think there's
always interesting stories there. Well,
your question make me like um kind of
like rewind to many many years ago. Uh I
just like graduated from high school and
uh to be honest, I'm I'm like not very
techsavvy at that time. Like I just I
just learned how to use the internet for
like the second or the third year. Um
uh and then um I came across this thing
called YouTube and then uh for some
divine intervention I just watched the
Microsoft vision 2020 video. So that was
like you can imagine like I mean we are
now in 2025. Uh but I was watching like
a a video of what Microsoft envisioned
2020 to be in 20 in in 2008. So,
and my 2008
high school self just got like blown
away uh with that video because it is
you know it starts with like you can
communicate with uh people in another
country. It's auto translated and then
uh there's this like you know like
transparent glass panel with text
popping up like oh your your your things
is done oh this person has this update
you'd see dashboard and everything
at that time it was just like
unfathomable
and so out of curiosity because I was
like like too was still amazed uh with
that thing I commented under the video
uh and says like uh wow this is such a
great video. I am a high school graduate
uh trying to figure out what should I
study for university. Can anybody tell
me what should I study in a university
just to be a part of this magic? And
then a stranger of a stranger in
internet whoever sees this comment um
that person replied that says you should
just go for computer science and I'm
like whoever that is thank you so much
you're one of the reason why I'm here
today uh as a data scientist and a
engineer in 2025
we need we all need to thank that that
YouTube commenter the magic on YouTube.
A gesture of kindness. Yeah. So it's
sparked by inspiration really
of magic making.
Okay. So from from there you you started
the traditional path of computer science
actually software engineering. So um
so at that time I was living in a small
town that is like 4 hours away from the
capital city. um of Malaysia, Koala
Lumpur. And so I picked one university
to go and study. Um but uh so you know
like at that time you do foundation in
IT and after one year um I I was going
to like computer science but then uh the
the school admission says hey you are
the only one who registered for computer
science do you mind like changing a
course?
And so I changed. Yeah. And so I changed
to software engineering. Um actually
software engineering with m with
multimedia. And so in that four years
um a fascinating tech came out which is
called uh AR and VR. So augmented
reality and virtual reality. And so me
and my friends we were just uh involved
in um like
just projects using augmented reality
and then we participated in you know
like Microsoft imagine cup and things
like this. Yeah. So that was bachelor's
time. Good time it's been some time.
Cool. And and then how because now you
are you're not in Malaysia anymore,
right?
Yes.
10 years. 10 years in Germany now.
Okay. And how how do you like Germany?
It's great.
Mhm.
I just saw one of the first Christmas
Christmas market booths
today that's getting set up. So yeah,
Christmas market is one of the things
that I look forward each year in
Germany. But yeah, Germany is for this
10 years. I think uh I really have to
thank this country for it because it
really
um grows me as a person. I feel like I I
feel like I've I've grown a lot in this
last 10 years
really. Okay. And you think uh that
Germany help you to to to grow
personally in in which way? M yeah I
would say fundamentally um because you
know like I I've basically uprooted
myself in one culture, one country, one
environment and then being put into like
such a different environment. And so I
think the greatest things that Germany
has made space for me is to
is to know who I am as a person, what I
prefer, what my thoughts and preferences
are and what do I want and then I can go
towards that. And so I would say in
general like this um individual
individuation
uh this is what uh Germany has given me
space to grow into.
Cool. Yeah. I I've lived in Germany as
well and I I think there are some some
very traditional aspects of of German
culture
but also there is um a big part of
letting
everyone be who they want to be
in all weird ways. they they accept and
are very
very particular you know and there is
not not that much judgment around that
compared to to other countries or other
cultures you know
yeah that's right and so like I I think
this is the the right place um that I'm
being put in to actually grow as a
person like I know I am not anybody's
shadow this way I'm just me Okay, cool.
I I I remember that you you shared with
me some some time ago that that maybe
you realized a few a few changes when
when you went back to to Malaysia after
after some time, right?
I mean, this happened to me as well when
I go back to my hometown, home own
place. After sometimes I realized I'm
I'm I'm not anymore the person was that
was living there and uh I cannot fit
anymore in that place because I grown in
different ways. Right.
Yeah. I think no matter where you go, if
you are an expat, um you feel like the
version of home that you that that you
were familiar with, but you leave um
will just be a snapshot in the past
because I mean Malaysia has grown so
much in these recent years. And so I
think as an expat no matter where you go
um you feel like you never belong in the
place that um you grow into but you're
also never home anymore because home as
has also evolved but I don't think that
is I don't think there's any issue with
that because this is the path that
all of us experts have chosen.
And what's most important is to
as long as you are feeling you uh and as
long as you're living authentically,
home is where you are. Home is not the
snapshot that you left alone with. Home
is also not like you don't necessarily
feel like 100% fitting in uh into
anything. But I am pretty sure like a
lot of locals will also share that uh
maybe they also don't feel like they fit
into the place that they have been like
growing up in.
So I think essentially
having this
having this experience just teach us
to realize that to realize that home is
really where you are.
Yeah, that's that's that's the goal,
right? I mean to to build your own where
where you are, be be good with with you,
which is a journey in in itself, I I
guess.
Yeah.
Interesting.
And where where in all this um AI fits?
Oh, okay. where what did we where what
where did we uh have the story last
time? Yeah, software engineering and I
came to Germany to study um intelligent
adaptive systems. So I started my
masters in the University of Hamburg in
2015 so 10 years ago. Um yeah so uh that
is um that three years uh is such a
eyeopener because that's when I really
learn the ins and outs like hardcore
research and application of machine
learning deep learning. I was working on
this uh humanoid robotics projects and
some sensors, you know, pairing that
with machine learning and training
humanoid robotics and doing computer
vision and all that.
What What do you think of uh the last um
humanoid robot thing that um came out
last week? I think this to me weird
robot with a with a sweater that
you know the Neo Neo I think it's called
the Neo something.
Yeah, I wouldn't give up things but the
the the humanoid robot uh the humanoid
robot that I was working on
uh also starts with N.
Okay.
Interesting.
Yeah. um you you guys sort of share very
similar names. Um but then
when I think about that version of the
robot with this version, I think
it it it needs some
maybe give it five more years uh for
another breakthrough. Um I think it's
more like maybe humanoid robotic is
developing a little bit you know needing
it is needing more time for all the
undeterministic
situations undeterministic scenarios in
real life. Um
so I feel that
yeah u
it takes much more time than than people
expect right
yeah but I think it's also the the the
perception the audience perception of it
because humanoid robotics is can it can
be borderline like uncanny you know and
so
and so the the mode of presentation has
to be a little bit careful because
if you if you present things like hey
you have a person that is maneuvering
the robot which means like what about
the privacy like I I um
that that's definitely unexpected.
Yeah.
Yeah. But I think that is the safest way
for the team
to actually
um
in a in a more controllable way
ensuring the accuracy of the humanoid
robot. And so I would give it some
grace, but I also totally understand how
uncanny it can feel when
when us just put ourself in the shoes of
the consumer of the user and then
extrapolate this presentation into what
might be in the future. Um, so yeah, if
you're if anybody is thinking about, you
know, [ __ ] the future is doom, I can
totally understand. Like this is just a
I think the handling of the presentation
into what the audience might feel like
that that that can be more considerate.
Yeah. But because the the the end goal I
mean not not everyone will will see it
the same way but most people would love
to have someone if it is a robot it's
fine to that do all the household stuff
for you right that that that is great
but it's I feel the technology will need
more time than than expected even if
Elon Musk I think will is saying that in
the next few years we'll be there in
every something like that. But you have
been working for example um on these
from 2015 right and you you think uh it
has advanced a lot in these 10 years or
it's a long incremental journey.
I don't think it's going to be
incremental. I think it's going to be
exponential uh from the rate of
development. Um
I think it still depends on how the
world is moving and being somebody who
have worked briefly um in human robotics
afterwards. I mean I have some years in
research um also in synthetic patient
data generation field.
What I think is I can almost hear two
sides of things. um one is the voice of
the rest of the world who are not in the
research and who are not in the work uh
having to apply it. Their their concern
is real
and so that should not be ignored. That
should be leaned in and listened to. It
has to be a dialogue um for how this um
for how this can be done in a way that
essentially is affecting everybody to be
honest. Um and people like voices from
all sides has to be considered. Um
but then on the other hand um for us who
are the practitioners of the field of
the tech
I see a lot of possibilities. I see a
lot of values to be done. Um especially
in the work that I do for clients right
now. Um what I see is
intention really matters and
what problems are you solving and for
who?
um humans have to come up with this
first and foremost and then the tech
comes in to you know make it make it
happen in reality. And so I think what
we can control right now is whoever is
needing this solution and whoever like
us is executing or implementing the
solutions figuring out for what and for
who. it's kind of our due diligence. Um,
and when it's done right, I do see a lot
of possibilities uh with the current LM
advancements. Uh, and it's just like the
the the the general um, you know, Gen AI
feel how it's evolving. Uh, it it is
really fascinating.
Yeah. I mean, we we of course share this
fascination, right? because we see all
the possibilities.
Um, but in the in the last years as this
has become an universal phenomenon and
everybody is is talking about generative
AI and all this stuff, there are all
sorts of of voices and things going on.
Uh people are scared or are um thoughts
around you know all these things. AGI
will will take um many jobs and
political things going on. So it's it's
a mess, right? We we enjoy it because we
we like to build things. I think that's
that's the spirit and we see it's just a
as a technology, right? Um but most
people which are not into this will hear
the news, hear whatever and understand
what they what they can with with the
information that they have. So there is
definitely a bridge there uh to to there
is a gap to to to fill between these two
uh words right and um yeah I guess as
you were saying it's it's important to
to pick the the right things uh in a way
um do it well but also communicate it in
in in the right way uh so that people
understand and don't have a weird
expectation or fears, you know, is that
something that that that you fe that the
that you feel uh when when you work with
with clients or uh interact with uh less
technical people?
You mean uh when deal when communicating
with less technical clients?
Um, am I understanding correctly that do
you think I feel that they care about
the for what and for who or how should I
how should I understand your question?
Yeah, if if you you feel that there is
um a disconnection between um how you
see this technology and what uh less
technical people expect from the
technology or what they uh think about
it if they have fears or
um how do you say yeah
for the clients I I come across usually
Um,
usually it is not like I go and pitch
that they need a solution. It's more
like they come to me that says they need
a solution. And so I would say in my
biased
small sample size experience
um there's less fear when a client comes
to me and said they need a certain
solution to be made. Um there can be you
know the application of machine learning
or even like statistics um like
traditional uh data insights,
predictive modeling or the bridge of
like taking predictive modeling insights
and then pair that with
um LM generation based on this insights.
Um but usually when they come to me they
already know what they want but then
it's up to us to say okay what is the
best way to go about it
do we care enough for the project to
carry on a good work for the client is
the for what and for who aligned with
the implement as well it's like do I
feel proud to put this piece of project
in my portfolio
uh I think this is then regarding the
fit
And if it doesn't fit, just feel free
to, you know, uh, politely excuse
yourself of this opportunity.
Uh, but then, um, what I am striving for
is
try to do things that
that are for good because this is part
of my values,
but for good is also kind of like, hey,
it's it can be anything. Um,
yeah.
But for me, it's kind of like
something that I told told a lot of our
members, our community members, is when
you look back at the things that you do,
even as a freelancer, content creator,
or whatnot, um it's okay to feel cringe,
but you don't really want to feel shame.
And so, it's kind of like
intention matters.
Okay. So what's what's an example of
something that you have been you have
worked on that you are proud of it?
Quite many.
So right now I am developing
a an automated tool for a consumer goods
company to
help their data scientists come up with
stability tests. So basically stability
test is like um you know when consumer
goods have a expiry date they have to
really like test their products over
some time and then use some algorithm to
come up with um expiry date. So to me I
feel like this is a meaningful project
because I get to save the data scientist
time who come up with expiry date for
consumer goods which these consumer
goods will be used by many many people.
And then another project that I help uh
to do is um the the pollutants
monitoring of the rin water uh system.
So basically like um basically like part
of Germany and the Netherlands share the
same water system and then um I helped
build sort of like a predictive modeling
tool to kind of like say hey can we you
know it's all sparse data so and then
data is kind of like inconsistent and
everything so a lot of processing is
involved but that tool now managed to
uh kind of like predict pollutants in
time to say like hey when a pollutant is
being detected abnormally at upstream
rivers then by this and this time it
it's going to flow to the border to the
Netherlands and things like this and so
this is something that
when being used correctly can really
benefit maybe the lives of per region of
people like I don't know I don't know
the future usage of this tool but the
implementation of it the intention
behind developing this kind of tools uh
in this project
oh sorry to interrupt
no all good so this is one of the one of
the examples of saying some of the
projects that I feel proud of
yeah yeah that that that makes sense
just um explain a bit uh the the
difference because that's where I think
it gets confusing for for people for
example for this last project is it um
generative AI is it deep learning it is
traditional machine learning um
statistical machine learning
okay what does it mean
it is not even
the classical machine learning like we
just use statistics as the background
algorithm of it.
Okay. So,
no geni,
Mhm.
no deep learning,
no neuron networks,
not even random forest. It's just pure
statistics.
Yeah.
Often times this is just enough to solve
the problem reliably.
Mhm. because there is maybe a tendency
now to use generative AI with these
large language models for to solve any
kind of problems or I there is this um
possibility at least right
and um from simple things like using CH
GPT as a as a consumer as a user and you
are asking it to to translate Apple to
Italian
and it's like using um I don't know
atomic bomb to to kill a mosquito right
I heard someone saying that
because we we I mean we can think about
it but um the normal people using chip
doesn't realize that it's it's a huge
technology right and there are data
centers and transformers and all
incredible technology behind it that
runs for for every simple uh
conversation that you have with JGPT,
right?
While for many many things it's it's not
needed that
so intelligent technology, you know what
I mean?
Yeah. But I would say that's a big
distinction between um
between the predictive modeling models
with uh Genai or LM models because
predictive modeling is largely
discriminative models and then the LM
like the things that you know Chad or
whoever's coined the term like AI the
big umbrella term they are largely
generative
And so they have different usage. So in
in terms of like what you say you know I
I want to do translation then a
generative model can do that very well
because um you know you can you can put
like a like a you know good prom and
then it's going to come up with an
equivalent version of like the
translation.
But then in predictive modeling projects
what it needs is not creativity. What it
needs is not generating new stuff but to
reliably based on past data points to
accurately predict things. So if you
take time series forecasting as an
example, uh maybe they have very sparse
data. They don't need a model
like an LM to tell, hey, can you help me
detect anomalies at which point in time
when this happens? Because a generative
model is most likely to make things up.
But a predictive model, a discriminative
model is going to train the model based
on the past data. And then if the
quality is good and if the model is has
been trained successfully, it can then
accurately predict in time uh what would
be the what would the ano
anomaly be? Yeah. So they are for kind
of like different usage and that is why
I think there are certain use cases for
um LMS there are certain use cases that
um the discriminative machine learning
models or statistical models will still
be in in demand because they are
inherently for different different
things.
What's the the current or or next thing
that you would like to to work on?
What's what that excites you right now?
What are you uh I don't know
experimenting with for a future client
project or
um I think right now I was still focused
on becoming a problem solver for worthy
problems. So
for every project that comes um it's
important for me to to satisfy
like to be convinced of the for what and
for who. So if you if you come with me
that says hey we we we want a water
pollutant monitoring system
to do this and it's going to be used by
uh used by this and this person.
If
I feel convinced of this like okay like
goes aligns with my values I'm going to
say yes because to me based on my
previous experience in academia in
industry I know where to look for
solutions
and so it's like right now the tools
that I have in my toolbox is machine
learning deep learning statistics
LMS engineering and so for all of those
things paired with software engineering
you can basically look for any solutions
you can you can come up with any
solutions but what I think is
um
as long as there is a worthy problem to
solve then it doesn't matter what does
it take because every
freelance project that I'm taking on
it's just so different and So back to
your question is kind of like it doesn't
matter what problem for me to solve. I
know I have the toolbox. I I have enough
cards to pull out and
fundamentally I know where to look for
solutions. Um and so for me right now
right now it's kind of like yeah if a
data science problem comes to me then
great. If a predictive modeling plus LM
um project comes to me then great. Um
I'm just looking for worthy problems to
solve.
So
back to to your beginning now you know
how to make the magic happen. So you're
more focused on make sure that it aligns
with you, right? You keep repeating this
for
for what and for
for who? Yeah. And so you you you just
search for alignment there. That's the
important part for you. And then you
know that you you have so many tools now
uh that you can find a solution, right?
Yeah, that's a very good uh depiction of
where I'm going. Uh I'm also I'm also
interested to you know like go back to
my main expertise which is computer
vision. I feel like that is getting so
much less practice since I left uh my
master's degree.
Okay. So, you would like to work on that
again?
Mhm.
Yeah. It would be great. It's so fun.
Yeah.
Yeah. Search for it, right? They are
Just need some good portfolio items and
then I will start applying.
Cool.
And um the I guess the the other correct
me if I'm wrong the other
big part for for you uh I don't know if
it is alpha alpha or or different is
helping other people
in their freelancing or business uh
journey right?
Yeah that's how we met.
Yeah that's how we met. Yeah.
and and yeah you shared with me many
things with about personal growth and
everything related to this kind of
journey but how how it started for you
uh when what you decided to I guess
before then that uh from what what I
know about your journey
when did you
started to have the desire or conviction
to uh be a freelancer, be independent,
uh something happened there.
So the first time that I I
dabble into freelancing was 2020 and at
that time
so I continue on the story uh that we
left off just now. I I started three
years uh for my masters
uh in intelligent adaptive systems and
afterwards I took on a full-time job as
a data science consultant which means my
company sent me to different
organizations and enterprises across
Germany to work on data science projects
um for those companies
and afterwards um in 2020 shortly before
that I feel like this doesn't align with
me so much. And so I quit.
Um and I said like I really want to you
know like try to be you know
establishing myself and see um how is it
being self-employed. Um and I tried
that. Um but at that time I feel like
it's also like how do you say it's also
like an opportunity come by where back
in my master's time I was already
interested in things to do with medical
healthcare with machine learning
and in the middle of doing freelancing
this PhD opportunity came to me and so I
took on this PhD opportunity and working
that many hours which means I have to uh
you know like give up on freelancing. Uh
but then I only took on this uh research
position for two years and then I
decided to quit again. So first
freelancing experience as in 2020 like
it doesn't last very long. I think at
most like half a year, one year and then
I started properly um after I end the
contract on this research position. Um
and that was
maybe 202
4. Oh wait, 2023 2024 304. So I was
being given a golden opportunity again
because that time Dave just happens to
open up this data freelancer program and
then I had the privilege to join the
program uh in the first year and I could
still remember how much Dave and the
community has helped me. You know in the
first year it's a smaller group and
everybody is kind of like very close
together. Um and Dave is like hosting
this Q&A calls like he still does um
today. And then I I started freelancing
properly using what was being taught in
the program. Like I essentially
apply tried to apply everything. Um, and
a year after that, I think
a year
after that, then Dave just says, "Hey,
we need a customer success manager and
coach. Um, would you be interested to
take on this position?" And then I was I
was just being humbled by the trust that
Dave uh put on me. I feel like Dave um
customer success is not written anywhere
on my resume.
But thanks for trusting me. It seems
like a very meaningful role to take on.
I'm willing to try. Like let's let's
give it a try. And now it's been like
one and a half years.
Okay. Yeah. Like there is so much I feel
to unpack there. uh when when you
started
uh freelancing and and you you you felt
that you needed help
uh so you you search for or you you come
across uh Dave uh from from YouTube I
guess.
Yeah.
And and and joined the program. What
what was that uh you needed back then?
M so when when Dave's program came out
um I actually before this so in 2020 I
already joined some like freelancing
programs but that one was more like it's
either general freelancing or like a
python based so it's not exactly like
machine learning so when Dave's program
is there I know that he's a data
scientist and he's um doing very
successfully in freelancing as a data a
scientist and his demeanor is just very
you know down to earth as we know and
very smart and then I like that he walks
the talk. Um that is the the the the
decision where I decided to kind of like
reach out and express my interest to
join a program. Um what I think I needed
at that time is to
is to essentially
see that I can do it
and I appreciate any kinds of guidance
that if anybody who has walked the talk
like walked this path before to see my
blind spot to give me some advice case
that I can apply for myself. Um this is
why like this is mainly why um the re
the the the relevance of the program
itself paired with thinking that I need
some
I need somebody experience who was on
this journey doing very successfully and
I can resonate with to help me to go
through this process.
Yeah, makes sense, right? And what what
are some um I guess limiting beliefs or
something that you personally struggle
with during during that that first year
is something that comes to mind or not?
Yes. I told Dave uh in a later
interview, I said uh Dave, I didn't have
confidence. I outsource my confidence to
you and thanks to you, I'm here. I'm in
the game.
I I think you you told me that phrase
the first time that we met. I wrote it
down and I
I I always remember that.
Yeah. And I'm trying to do that to all
the community members now. Like I'm like
I know what you need um based on based
based on the fact that I'm also in the
game.
Um
And so
if you
if you can leave the rest to us and then
just say I want to go here, we'll help
you get there. And so in a way uh I'm
trying to be outsourced the confidence
as I as I unknowingly outsourced they my
confidence before. Yeah.
Yeah. we are now passing on right to to
to us to to the other rest of the people
in in the community.
Yeah. But I also think it's my pleasure
like it it it is just such a pleasure to
to witness everybody's journey because
oh it's better than movies is better
than watching movie movies.
I look at your experience, I look at
your journey like um from the first time
that we talk
and until today you have grown a lot and
you have also achieved some things along
the way
and so this takes like you know you see
a real life scenario in different people
you see the stories in different people.
Um
I think
I think my role is just to remind
everybody
what they know already within themsel. I
just reinforce that Nicola based on what
we talk I think you are this and this
person. Um, if this is your goal, I help
you hold the the your your ideal self in
my mind. And in my mind, every goal that
you told me that you're going to
achieve, I consider it I consider it
done already. And now I'm just walking
this process with you. But in my mind,
it's already done. and I'm just waiting
for one day in the future that you'll
come back to tell me that says I'm
already in my ideal self and and I'll be
just like, you know, I knew it. I knew
it a long time ago.
Yeah, that that makes sense. But um
what now that you have seen people going
going through this, what what are the
skills to be coachable?
What are the skills to be coachable?
Wow, that's such a great question. Let
me think.
I think it's mostly
the humility
to see a different perspective of the
story.
What do you mean?
a lot of people.
Um, so
in my experience, I feel that I cannot
help those people
who cannot believe in another
version of narration.
So
what they want is
I'm stuck here.
don't convince me otherwise and then
they try to
they're not receptive
to the other things. So I would say
first of all the humility to accept that
reality has different narration and you
just have to
rather than seeing it as good or bad
see it as pros and cons
and then see yourself as one avatar in
the sandbox and says I'm here this is
where I want to go what is beneficial
for me to take And people with nar a
certain narration they are very you know
very convinced of something
when I see that it this convincing
reality
does not serve them uh and if they if
they are not ready to accept other
possibilities other narration that says
hey maybe you can look into here and
that um I I think if they are very
if if they decide to stay in this
narration, there's nothing that I can
do.
I see.
Yeah. Oh, so this is one. Second would
be accountability.
Okay.
This is what we do every week, Nicola.
I know that part well.
Okay. But
accountability, do they follow up? Do
they follow through um with with the
things that they should be doing? They
said they would do.
Yeah. So,
because action moves the needle, right?
Mhm.
Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Of course. I I was
curious to to dig a bit deeper on on the
first part that you uh what you said,
right? So I'm hearing that if someone
as
their own narration,
so it like a story that they tell
themselves and they they are not willing
to see another story,
but they want to to get somewhere
uh to their goals. and you you help them
realize that uh to get there they need
to to change uh the narration
right so if they are not flexible in
that way or they don't listen that there
is another
uh narration there is another story that
serves you better to to get there
um
it's difficult to to about someone stuck
in that situation. Is that what what you
mean?
Yeah. So if they if they feel that it is
more
it is more valuable to hold on to the
current narration that put them in
current situation and they are not ready
to
see elsewhere. You know, like even to be
open for the possibility the other
generation of maybe there's some other
things that you can still try or maybe
there is some interpretation of your
assumptions uh that you can maybe tweak
a little bit maybe
maybe that that can be that can move you
forward a little bit. So um
yeah, so if if they
if they feel more secure by holding on
to this
this narration,
um I will honor that. I will make space
I I will make space for that as well to
say that it's okay. I can see that
you're not ready to
to to explore or this narration. um uh
at this moment. And so um
I I I feel that it is also important to
make them feel okay that this narration
right now that
they they hold like they hug like
hugging a lock just to not drown. Um,
it's okay to acknowledge that and give
space for them to do this until they are
ready again.
Okay. Yeah.
Yeah. I recognize you're you have this
um
way of helping people.
Uh yeah that is uh you know everyone has
their own uh
way of going through coach someone in in
these situations right uh there are some
more I don't know how to call it more
strict in a way uh but you can
go and and take someone from where they
are
uh as you've said acknowledge that they
In this moment they might need something
else right that you cannot force them uh
right that is a more gradual journey
uh that comes with with whatever time
and type of journey uh someone needs
right
have you heard about the story of the
mushroom man
mushroom? No.
Okay. So tell me um
I've watched this story from the
internet so I don't know where to site
this from but this story stuck with my
head
and I've been I've been secretly
applying to all of you guys all along.
Oh let's see.
So
so the mushroom man is
there's a guy who is so convinced that
he is a mushroom he's not a human. Okay.
So, a guy is so convinced that he's a
mushroom and so he just take this
umbrella and then just stood on one side
all along like he just wants to be a
mushroom. Like he's so convinced that
he's a mushroom.
Yeah.
And then of course other people who care
for him will say like you're not a
mushroom, you're human. Like come on.
It's like look at yourself. You don't
look like a mushroom. But that guy is
just so convinced to be a mushroom and
nobody can change his mind. Um, and so
one day a person comes along
and just take another umbrella and just
sit next to him.
And then that mushroom guy said, "Hey,
what are you doing here?" And then that
guy just says like, "I'm also a
mushroom."
And then that guy says, "Huh? Oh, we're
mushroom friends now." And then after,
you know, sitting sitting with that guy
for for some time that that guy just
started to stand and walk.
And then the mushroom man just freaked
out. And then that mushroom man is like,
"Hey, you're a mushroom. How can you do
this?" And then that guy just said, "You
don't know. It's 2025. Mushrooms can
walk."
And then that guy says, "Huh,
interesting. are you okay? Mushroom can
walk. And he said, "Of course, all
mushrooms can walk this year, starting
this year." And then that mushroom guy
just stand up and walk.
And so the moral of the story is
um
righteousness is not my goal in
coaching. um the intention to making
somebody um seeing the potential in
somebody that this person is not a
mushroom, it's a human and he has the
place that he needs to go. Um I don't
have to be right. I just have to try my
best to have the intention to get this
person into where they want to go.
Yeah. Now it it makes Yeah, definitely.
It's how we are helping us. It makes
sense.
Now you know my trick.
Yeah.
No, this is great. Yeah. Like I mean
it's these stories help you to fix fix
some some ideas but know I I see uh you
know where where
from where you you come from and uh
different people need different things.
Someone works better with a carrot and
stick approach and someone it's it's a
mush someone is a mushroom and they need
a different approach to this uh yeah
that yeah I can relate to that makes
makes sense and
yeah it just happened that I don't have
to be right. I don't have to I don't
need to have another people told me that
I'm right
for me to feel good about myself. Like I
just like I care about another person
and for this care uh I would do my best.
I know I know my goal my goal is not to
be right.
Mhm. Is to to get someone where they
want to go. Yeah. Okay. Cool. So that's
that's let's let's say the first uh
skill that that that you mentioned
and the second important one is
accountability right
and and so why some of us
as everyone
some sometimes we we are not able to do
what we say that uh we want to do why we
need that accountability
accountability
helps you make progress and there can be
many reasons why
you cannot do what you wanted to do. You
might be lacking
skills. You might be lacking some tools.
You might be lacking the permission that
only you can give to yourself. And
another people just have to remind you
that um
the power is not outside, the power is
inside.
M
and these are the things that I think in
life we just rely on the kindness of
another person to help you move forward.
And that is how we
that is how we choose to interact with
the world to
to be willing to accept the goodness
from other people and then pass it
forward.
Okay.
Okay. Yeah. You're I was I was expecting
a totally different uh totally different
answer and I'm realizing Yeah. that I
don't know it in the couple last days
I'm now I'm connecting random dots
[Music]
excuse me if it doesn't make sense but
no I think it makes some sense because
there when I think about accountability
or these kind of topics
uh coaching and and people going through
some personal development journey I feel
the
predominant narrative online, especially
YouTube or the the influences that I see
thanks to the algorithm algorithm of
whatever are quite strong, right? You
know, more masculine energy in a way
the Tony Robbins or
this kind of motivational stuff, right?
Make sense? Mhm.
While
in in your answer, I feel definitely a
different energy uh that is not the
predominant one because predominant is
louder and definitely
more masculine. I I feel there
at least uh yeah, as I said, what what
we see online etc is more men doing
this. at least what what I receive from
the algorithm and while the your angle
is is is different in this. Yeah. And
it's it's a it's good that there is
another angle, right? And that we
normally don't don't see
what
Yeah. I'm glad that I contribute a
little bit to that. Uh but I also see
that um I think you just have to look um
advice like this also exists on the
internet. Um I think it's more like if
if you don't realize like you just don't
know what you don't know. I think this
happens with a lot of people and
especially the the design of the
algorithm is more like bubble like like
you get more of what you look at and
what you consume and so you you know
from time to time look the other side.
Yeah.
You have some recommendation for the
other side. What what what are some
resources or some people that influenced
you?
Oh, resources and people. Um,
I don't know where do I start. It's like
in the in which topic.
Yeah, in this kind of uh I think now we
are in the personal development uh or
doing something that you have never done
before.
In this case, it's uh your business,
your freelance journey. M
and so there is that struggle to do
something that you have not done before
and so you might need what we are
talking about right changing your story
accountability someone that helps you. M
so in this realm of
personal growth
what uh most influenced you or you like
to read look up to go back to
I am currently reading so go back to I
have one principle book that helped me
like that is the guiding light uh of of
my life and then some supplementary
books and Um
but yeah I can share them. So my guiding
principle resource is a diamond sutra by
the Buddha and then I am currently
reading I'm currently reading taqing by
la.
Um but they are very meta. They're very
they're very like they're for people
like me who always contemplate the
meaning of life and but the third one
but the third one that I can recommend
is uh the way of integrity by Marta
Beck.
Okay. What can you tell me about these
three books? Or I'm curious about the
first one since it's your um guiding
principle. What
what there is in there.
The Diamond Sutra essentially says that
um everything tangible that you can see
in this world
um is kind of like it's ever changing.
So it's kind of like a dream. It's kind
of like a dew and like a morning dew.
It's kind of like um illusion. It's kind
of like a shadow. Um it's kind of like
uh thunder. Um and we should see the
world this way. And so that has given me
that has given me a sense of saying that
I should not kind of like try to cling
on something.
um I should be really fluid like if I
want to uh enjoy the world the right
way. Um and so one of the stories in
there says if you're drowning and then
you happen to hug a lock like a big
piece of wood and then that has saved
your life. Um but then since you're now
safe like you're not drowning anymore
you have come to the land but maybe out
of security you feel like this lock is
so important for you it has saved your
life so you just hug it to walk it but
who knows your next quest is to climb
the mountain like you cannot since the
lock has saved you already you should
let it go because your next quest is
climbing a mountain that lock is not
going to serve you.
And so that main guiding principle is
kind of like say
everything is as is happened. Um for
example, our podcast now is as happened.
It's going to end in I don't know like
20 minutes time
and I should not cling on it. I should
not think about oh damn I should change
something about it. Like also in
freelancing it's like in freelancing
you have to have a level of grace uh and
compassion to yourself for the courage
to come out. If you always say that I
have to be perfect I cannot make any
mistakes. Sorry. You live in a
classroom. You're not living in the real
world. Um if you're living in the real
world and you don't want to get to
insanity.
Just try to
do a small experiment. see what it comes
back and if it is not the outcome that
you want just pivot and do better next
time. So like don't hug the lock when
you have to climb the mountain. Yes, the
lock has saved you. It has served you in
the past but time to move on.
Yeah, that that's a that's a great
metaphor. Yeah.
Yeah. So, it's kind of like
I don't see you, Nicola, as Nicola the
coachi because I know it just happened
in this moment that we met and I'm being
put in a position to give you some
advice and you're in the position of
needing some advice. But this is not
forever. Like, this is not permanent. At
some point, these
three that I look after will grow. Like,
you're going to be a different Nicola.
And I don't see you Nicola as the first
version anymore. Like I should see you
as an everchanging. And it this is this
is the
this is what I think
the the way that I prefer to look at
life everything like people person
environment everything.
Makes me think of it. I feel it's kind
of a translation of this um that what
serves served you to to get here won't
serve you to get
somewhere else right we have different
whatever phases
challenges
uh grow path and something you need
something to get somewhere h but then it
won't help you to get somewhere else
because it's constantly evolving journey
and challenges and and stuff. Yeah.
Perfect. This is a perfect
interpretation.
Yeah. And what what about the what was
the the third book that that you
mentioned?
The way of integrity by Marta Beck.
And what's the the message from there?
That one
the message is to really honor your own
truth.
And so, uh, it described like this
theater play by it's called Inferno. Um,
so I think it's like maybe it's Italian
story, you know, like maybe let me know.
I I look into it. I mean, the the
inferno from from Dante is where it all
started. Yeah,
it's from Dante. Yeah. M
so that book is about taking Dante's
inferno into examining our life. And so
it says that it it goes through
you have to go through the center of the
earth
and then go to the inferno and then
coming out from the other side. And so
that book is such a
supernova for me like
because
um
back then I just take every advice as is
and thinking that if I apply them um I'm
going to get success or get happier. But
I forgot to examine myself like if that
advice is made for me or not. like do I
see myself in this or do I have a level
of understanding
that this thing fits me or not. Um and
the process of doing that is then to
to find the truth slowly and that book
the way of integrity. It's basically
like explaining or practicing or making
you realize what are the ways that you
can find your own integrity. And so you
have this inner truth as your anchor and
everything has to filter through this
and then you get a sense of clarity.
um when dealing with a lot of noise.
I see. So, it's like helping you to
um filter the advice and what are
what are people telling you instead of
following uh everyone in all in every
direction.
Yeah. Yeah. It's more like there are two
kinds of heart. Um there are two kinds
of hardness
um that that we face. Um one kind of
hard is if you're a fish then if you
want to swim to the ocean and then you
know like it's a different environment.
You just have to push on right like you
have a you know you be stronger as a
different as a stronger fish you maybe
swim faster or anything. But another
kind of heart is you don't know who you
are. You don't even know you're a fish.
And then you're trying to compete with
monkeys climbing the tree. And then
you'll be stuck thinking why are the
other monkeys just seem so so light and
easy and so effortless in climbing the
trees because you don't even know like
and and you're kind of out of breath.
You're not as good as they are. You're
not achieving the height that they are,
but you're half dying. Uh that's because
you don't realize that you're a fish
like this is not your lane like go back
to the water like and and you know swim
towards the ocean.
Yeah.
Did you did you
experience some something like that?
There was there was a time where you
felt you were trying
Yeah.
to do
three times.
Yeah. Okay.
three times that I have to be almost
bedridden.
I'm in a lot of pain uh to realize uh
I'm not supposed to do certain things.
And usually that comes in terms of
um
the career choice
um and the environment
and uh my
attitude trying to climbing the trees.
uh while not knowing myself. So yeah, I
have had three burnouts in the past 10
years and the first one was
um during my software engineering time
and the second one was during my PhD
time and no
during my uh data science consultant
time and third time was during my PhD
time. Uh
And what did you realize why you were um
what
made it clear for you that you were
doing what you were not supposed to do
or was not.
I realized that
I I never think about checking in with
myself
if
if being in an environment or doing a
certain thing will make me respect
myself more or less.
So I didn't
So it's more like I keep looking out and
then I tried doing things and I tried to
come up with a good result, good
performance.
Um
but then I don't know what I'm made of.
Um so it's kind of like
it's kind of like I am trying my very
best
just trying to survive instead of
driving
and that comes in many many ways maybe
it is with
the pace of the project maybe it's with
the nature of the project maybe it's
with the nature of the environment of
what is demanded of you Um and
and these kind of
uh self-awareness came uh after taking
me three excruciating physical pain um
to to realize that maybe I should look
at what I'm made of.
So you you feel you were ignoring maybe
earlier signals, right? I'm ignoring all
the subtle and obvious signals
that until my body literally can't move
anymore
for me to say stop.
Otherwise, I'll still keep moving. Like
otherwise, I wouldn't have learned this
lesson. So, my body was compassionate
enough to take a breakdown
to remind myself that hey, this is not
you. like this is you're not
it you're you're you're a different
vehicle being put on different purpose.
Yeah. What what are those signals that
someone in in a similar situation might
catch before getting to
um
at at first I would say it is
little discomfort here and there and
that might come in terms of emotions
that might comes in terms of sensations.
Um and then uh the next thing would be
you're trying to overcome them but you
feel that you are slowly giving up on
yourself or betraying yourself like you
you're ser kind of like betraying your
own truth um in order to get better if
that make any sense. Um
and then you keep
giving in. So you slowly find yourself
m
grinding
more like
more like you more like you feel like
you grind yourself off that nothing is
left like you're you're you're slowly
losing your life force instead of um
instead of feeling like
I'm still myself doing this.
Yeah. It's going to feel like
I keep running and running and running
but for what?
And maybe your logical brain is going to
convince you ah it's for this you know
this
um
nice achievement
and it's for me to prove to myself that
I can do this. Um
but yeah um this is going to
this is kind of like a slippery slope
where you you betray yourself again and
again and again.
Yeah.
Yeah. And
those are the signs.
Definitely
it happens.
Those are the signs and then you you
wake up and then you think like why am I
doing this? Like like where am I?
Yeah. Exactly. I wanted to say exactly
the same,
but it happened to me in the in the past
going
into work in the morning,
you know, you you get there, you sit at
your desk, you look around, and you say,
"What am I doing here?"
Yeah. Time to look inside.
Yeah.
There's a message for you. Read the
message.
I see. And so you it's interesting you
you you said that this happened to you
um three times. So it was different
things that you discovered
or you went you went back to uh
something similar that I don't know uh
catch you in a different way.
Same feeling, different environment,
different faces, different projects, but
the feeling is the same.
The feeling is that
I didn't stop myself right there
and allow myself to do the things or be
somewhere or well generally do something
that make myself respect me less.
That's the that the that's the question
that I didn't think of questioning
myself back then. If this would be my
decision filtering process that would
make a lot of life easier.
I see. And there there were there was a
part of you
in the second and or third time that
says
why you you felt again into this or or
not.
No, second and third time I managed to
catch myself easier. Um and being
different from the first time, the first
time is kind of like I just graduated
university. This is my very first job. I
have to do my very best as a A+ student,
you know, like score perfectly uh for
everything that I do.
Um
when I had the first burnout, I actually
doubted myself like I actually asked
myself like why am I so useless? Like
why can't I do this? Um but second and
third time, no like second and third
time it's like ah there it goes again. I
thought I have pivoted but looks like I
have not pivoted enough.
I see. Okay,
makes sense. There there was some
you feel external pressure especially in
the first time or something that you
um
that it was coming from
from the past or something that you'd
learned when when you were younger um
that you needed to be this A+ student uh
score everything at uh the best you felt
like some external pressure back then.
I wouldn't think it's an external
pressure. I think it is more like the
I misunderstood myself.
um only recently two to three years ago
that
I change my perspective on my existence
in the world.
So
only up until two to three years
ago,
I used to think that my existence is to
be of use by others, is to
lose my shapes and forms and then
putting myself down to the dust and to
just serve others. And that is love
and that is contribution.
And that was my thinking
back then. Um
and yeah, well since this last two to
three years, I've changed a lot.
I'm living a much better life right now.
Uh and continue to do better. But yeah
um that that that
shift in perspective that I am my own
person. I have my shapes and forms and
boundaries. This is where I end. This is
where others start.
Uh I can have my own preference. Uh I
exist in the world. Therefore
I have the right to interact with the
world as me.
Um, that might sound crazy for a lot of
people hearing this right now, but this
is seriously, if I want to be totally
honest,
I only started
embodying that two to three years ago.
Yeah, I I think it most people are are
struggling with that is is not not
strange or maybe it's strange for
someone because they have not thought
about that.
But uh
maybe
I'm not going that I'm irreversible
anymore.
I'm not going back. Never ever.
Of course not. Yeah.
No.
Yeah. That's yeah that's amazing that
that
you have been able to to do that you
know it takes
it takes um some people it takes a lot
of time and
you don't even realize because when when
the past you
were not realizing was not realizing
what was happening right uh or not fully
uh to be able to to break out of it and
as you said understand your boundaries
and that you exist for yourself with
your own tastes and goals etc etc
you're not living just for the others
and it's amazing to see you shine now
and I'm so curious to to see where this
path with with lady lead you Mhm.
I would love you to share more of this
because it's it's so important and you
you explaining in such easy and
understandable terms.
Sure. We'll be glad to.
Yeah,
we'll be glad to. Let's see how things
go. But I'm feeling hopeful. I'm feeling
very hopeful. I
know.
That's great. Okay. I think it does this
is um a nice ending.
Thank you so much for for the
conversation.
I thank more about you and uh you have
shared so many interesting things. I
hope people can
um use them
to to grow them themsel as well.
Yeah really Nicola thank you so much for
inviting me to do this. Uh I am not used
to talk about myself. I hope this ends
well. But in any case, I've enjoyed our
conversation today and uh thank you for
having me.
Thank you. Free. Bye. Bye.